<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certaine advertisements and articles, giuen by the Worshipfull Master Robert Iohnson Archdeacon of Leicester. In the visitation holden for the said archdeaconrie, at the feast of the Annunciation of our blessed lady the Virgine Marie in the yeare of our Lord God 1613. and the of reigne of our most gracious Lord King Iames, by the grace of God of England, France and Ireland, Defender of the Faith, &amp;c. the eleuenth, and of Scotland the fortie fiue..</title>
            <author>Church of England. Archdeaconry of Leicester. Archdeacon (1591-1625 : Johnson)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B07639</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 180867067</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10222</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S92356</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">180867067</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocn 180867067</idno>
            <idno type="VID">191720</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B07639)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 191720)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2284:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certaine advertisements and articles, giuen by the Worshipfull Master Robert Iohnson Archdeacon of Leicester. In the visitation holden for the said archdeaconrie, at the feast of the Annunciation of our blessed lady the Virgine Marie in the yeare of our Lord God 1613. and the of reigne of our most gracious Lord King Iames, by the grace of God of England, France and Ireland, Defender of the Faith, &amp;c. the eleuenth, and of Scotland the fortie fiue..</title>
                  <author>Church of England. Archdeaconry of Leicester. Archdeacon (1591-1625 : Johnson)</author>
                  <author>Johnson, Robert, 1540-1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ambrose Garbrand.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title page ornament, head- and tail-pieces, initials.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B².</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England. --  Archdeaconry of Leicester --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Pastoral letters and charges --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:191720:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:191720:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:191720:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:191720:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:191720:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:191720:3"/>
            <p>CERTAINE AD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VERTISEMENTS AND Articles, giuen by the Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Maſter <hi>Robert Iohnſon</hi> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacon of Leiceſter.</p>
            <p>In the Viſitation holden for the ſaid Archdeaconrie, at the feaſt of the Annunciation of our bleſſed Ladie the Virgine MARIE in the yeare of our Lord God 1613. and of the Reigne of our moſt gracious Lord King IAMES, by the grace of God of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, France and Ireland, Defender of the Faith, &amp;c. the eleuenth, and of Scotland the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie fiue.</p>
            <p>LONDON Printed for <hi>Ambroſe Garbrand.</hi> 1613.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:191720:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:191720:4"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:191720:5"/>
            <head>The vſe of the Eccleſiaſticall Viſitations.</head>
            <p>ORdinarie Viſitations Eccleſiaſticall by what authoritie ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer executed, were originally inſtituted and ordained for the honour of God, the good of his Church, and the preſeruation of the people of God in vnitie of true Religion, and in holineſſe of life and conuerſation, and that the Churches Parochiall &amp; other foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and erected for diuine worſhip, might by Eccleſiaſticall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates and Church-gouernours in their diſtinct callings be furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with reuerent and diſcreet Miniſters, godly and learned Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, faithfully to teach and inſtruct the people in the truth of Gods word, ſincerely to adminiſter the Sacraments, and to doe and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme all other offices of the holy Church, by name Matrimonie, viſiting the ſicke, buriall of the Dead, thankeſgiuing of Women after childbirth, and ſuch like, according to the poſitiue Lawes and Ordinances of Chriſtian Kings and Princes, Gods Vicegerents on the earth, without any Antichriſtian corruption, Schiſmaticall innouation of addition of their owne. And further that in due exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, or ſuch Viſitations, the enemies of Gods truth, the Papall, Schiſmaticall, Anabaptiſticall, prophane or other, might be refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med or expulſed Gods Church: All idle and diſſolute Miniſters (being inſufficient and a ſcandall to their calling) remoued and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placed, and men or better ſort, ſobrietie and worthineſſe, placed in their ſtead: and that the people who are many times careleſſe and negligent to be inſtructed, &amp; oft ſeduced to follow innouation and ſtrange worſhip, might be reduced from their errours and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, eyther by godly exhortation and perſwaſion, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by the cenſures of the Church. This diuine and verie neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie inquiſition by the prouidence of God and in wiſedome of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times grauely ordained being duly executed by the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, Miniſter, Churchwardens, &amp; ſuch other as are truſted in this buſineſſe, would doubtleſſe God aſſiſting eaſily purge the Church of many inconueniences, and bring the people to better obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and more due acknowledgement of the benefits beſtowed vpon them, in placing ouer them ſo renowned, ſacred and religious a Prince, and in giuing vnto them by his ſole wiſedome and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie vnder God, libertie to ſerue God, and to liue at home in peace.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:191720:5"/>
            <head>¶ An Aduertiſement.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hankeſgiuing for benefits and graces recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and daily inuocation of Gods holy name for the continuance of his bleſſings towards vs, and for the protection and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of this Church, Prince, and People, from the rage, oppreſſion, and violence of Satan and his members, as it is particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commanded in many places in holy writ, ſo it is warranted vnto vs by all examples of the Prophets and Patriarches in all ages, &amp; therefore ſince we haue as good cauſe as euer nation had to proſtrate our ſelues before the Maieſtie of the Almightie for the infinite bleſſings brought vpon vs, in placing ouer vs ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, ſacred and godly a Prince, as no Chronicle can euer mention, neither any Kingdome or people euer had: let vs ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeriouſly, yea let vs ſincerely euen from the bottoms of our hearts acknowledge with all thankſgiuing the good receiued, which we ought euen of our owne accord to do: yet much more when we are commanded by publike authoritie. And therefore for as much as we are by certaine ſtatutes, proclamations, let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and ordinances required, enioyned and commanded, to celebrate the day of his Maieſties Coronation, and of his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull deliuerance from that bloody conſpiracy of that family of the <hi>Gowries,</hi> as alſo from that moſt horrible, trecherous and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable action of that Antichriſtian, helliſh &amp; moſt damnable plot and practiſe lately intended, not againſt the perſon of his Maieſtie onely, but to the quite extirpation &amp; ſubuerſion of his royall iſſue, Religion, and the whole ſtate of this Kingdome: it behooueth euery Miniſter &amp; all Church-officers, be they Church-wardens or other, as they tender their dutie to God, their alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance to their Prince, &amp; their obedience to the lawes eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, to prouide that in their ſeuerall Pariſhes and Cures, all ſolemnitie be had of the day of his Maieſties Coronation, and all publike prayer be vſed according to the preſcript forme ſet forth by authoritie as well the fift of Auguſt, as vpon the fift of Nouember, and that a particular note be giuen by the Miniſter
<pb facs="tcp:191720:6"/> and Churchwarde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of al ſuch as ſhall refuſe to come to Church thoſe daies: and for their better admonition it is required that the Miniſter doe make knowne vnto the people vpon the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Sunday the ſeuerall daies as they ſhall happen to fall.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Church recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants enemies to Gods truth, to be preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note>1 Church-Recuſants, as it is a name heretofore ſeldome or neuer heard of, ſo are they in the condition and practiſe of their life, knowne enemies of Gods truth, ſuch as hate to heare the word, or partake the Sacraments, and liue in open contradic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and oppoſition againſt the lawes of God, and againſt the lawes of their Chriſtian Prince and Common-welth. Theſe perſons being iuſtly reputed very dangerous ſubiects and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſiue members in the Church, are by the Miniſter &amp; Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens with all care and diligence to be enquired after, and preſented by their knowne names &amp; ſurnames, with addition of their titles, and with declaration of what power and ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie they are, and what office they beare in the Church and Common-wealth, which preſentment ſo made is to be ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed and deliuered vnder the hand of the Miniſter, Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens and Sworne men.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">Admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſuch as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vpon refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented.</note>2 Where ſundrie perſons who haue béene héeretofore Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſants, doe now of their owne accord frequent the Church, though not ſo vſually as others, &amp; yet refuſe to heare the word preached, or to receiue the Sacrament of the Lords Supper the better thereby to confirme them, and to giue teſtimonie vnto others by thoſe their outward actions of that their inward zeal, deuotion and conformity, it behoueth the Miniſter and Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens in like ſort, firſt by godly admonition to perſwade the ſaid perſons if ſo they can, to receiue, or otherwiſe to preſent all ſuch as ſhal obſtinately refuſe, being of the age of ſixtéene years and aboue, leaſt their ſufferance and permiſſion of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come an offence vnto the godly, and giue others cauſe by their example to backſlide.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">Wiues, Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating ought to be preſented.</note>3 Though ſundrie Recuſants haue of late conformed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and doe now come to the Church to heare diuine praier, and to receiue the Sacraments, as by the lawes of God, and of this Realme they are commanded: yet the wiues, children, and family of many of thoſe reformed Recuſants doe notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſtill continue obſtinate, and will not be drawne eyther by the example of the huſband, parent, or maſter, nor by any other godly perſwaſion or conference to doe and performe what to
<pb facs="tcp:191720:6"/> them &amp; euery of them in a Chriſtian dutie to God &amp; the Prince belongeth. For reformation whereof the Miniſter, Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, and Sworn-men are to take a true note and particular of euery ſuch perſon in thoſe families as ſhall refuſe to come to Church, or to receiue the Sacraments, being of lawfull age and hauing no iuſt impediment, ſhall accordingly preſent them.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The infection of Recuſancy being the very fruit and badge of Antichriſtian irreligon, hath béene a ſurfet ſo long and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous in this Kingdome, as by the daily increaſe of ſuch as affect thoſe dregs of Popery, the diſeaſe and contagion ſéemeth in it ſelfe incurable, and the rather for that the ſeuerall houſes of Recuſants here infected for the better ſtrengthning of that cauſe as is ſuppoſed,<note place="margin">Marriages of Recuſants and their children not publikely ſolemnized, to be preſented.</note> doe vſually couple and ioyne themſelues in Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonie together, and ſo are growne by that vnion and coniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to a great ſtrength and kindred; now for as much as theſe marriages are moſt times in priuate houſes celebrated without any publike licence or banes aſking: and the Children likewiſe begotten betwixt ſuch perſons are ſeldome or not at all in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like baptized: It is thought fit and very conuenient, that the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter and Churchwardens of euery Pariſh doe very carefully informe themſelues of all ſuch marriages ſo ſuppoſed to be had and of all ſuch Children ſo baptized, that the ſeuerall perſons herein Culpable may be preſented, and compelled to prooue by lawfull teſtimony their ſeuerall marriages, that their Children are baptized according to the Ordinances of the Church now e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed, or otherwiſe to endure ſuch puniſhment and penalty as by the lawes Eccleſiaſticall of this Realme in ſuch caſe is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiouſly prouided: the law it ſelf requiring a due and perfect re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter continually to bee kept by the Miniſter and Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, of all marriages and Chriſtenings had within the Pariſh, and to be yearely ſent into the Biſhops Regiſter there to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Now for the auoyding of the future euill which may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen in ſuch caſe, it is required that the Churchwardens and ſworn-men of euery Pariſh doe inquire and informe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues what Miniſters other then ehe Parochiall Miniſter doth vſually celebrate diuine ſeruice,<note place="margin">Strange Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Scholemaſters frequenting the houſes of Recuſants to be preſented.</note> adminiſter the Sacraments and performe other Church Offices, in thoſe priuate Families, and whether the ſaid perſon ſo executing ſuch offices bée a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter licenſed, and haue ſubſcribed to the Articles of Religion,
<pb facs="tcp:191720:7"/> and if not to preſent him; &amp; further what ſchoolemaſters the ſaid families being noted for Recuſancy haue to teach their Childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and what licenſe the ſaid ſchoolema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſters haue ſo to doe, for that many tranſformed Ieſuites, and Seminaries, vnder the name and colour of ſchoolemaſters, doe vſually frequent ſuch places, and in the Cloake and couert thereof doe exerciſe al their ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious ſeruice and Idolatrous practiſes.</p>
            <p n="6">6 For as much as ſome prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; haue informed (as it ſéemeth) the Kings moſt excellent Maieſtie and the Honorable Lords &amp; other of his Highnes priuy Councel,<note place="margin">All excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants vpon Oath for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie to be abſolued.</note> that ſundry Recuſants be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate perſons would willingly come to the Church &amp; receiue the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in caſe they might obtaine their abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of excommunication inflicted, it is thought fit &amp; hereby required that the Miniſters of euery Pariſh, Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, or Hamlet, within this Dioces doe forthwith, or ſo ſoone as with conueniency they may, giue publike notice in the Church or otherwiſe to the perſons the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues or at their manſion houſes, that if they will come to the Ordinary who did excommunicate them, or being not able to come will procure commiſſion to bee granted for their better eaſe to their particular Miniſter, and take oath for their after-conformitie, they ſhall bee abſolued without fée: ſo as they haue commited no other offence which doth deſerue ſome publike reformation or ſatiſfaction to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation.</p>
            <p n="7">7 Laſtly for as much as Schiſme and deuiſion in Religion and in the Ceremonies of the Church hath &amp; doth much diſturbe the peaceable gouernment of the ſame,<note place="margin">One vniforme order of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayer, &amp;c. wherein default is to be preſented.</note> and doth likewiſe giue great occaſion to the profeſſed enemies of Gods truth thereby to withdraw the people and ſuch as are weake from the Religion, doctrine &amp; diſcipline of the Church now eſtabliſhed, for that we are not (as they pretend vnto them) at vnitie within our ſelues, it is very neceſſary and behouefull, that ſithence it hath pleaſed the Kings moſt excellent Maieſtie by his late Canons exempli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied vnder the broad ſeale of England, to decrée and ſet downe that one vniforme order in the execution of diuine ſeruice and in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> adminiſtration of the Sacraments, of apparel, as of Church ornaments and Ceremonies, ſhould be vſed by the Cleargie of this Kingdome, as well in the publike execution of thoſe their particular offices as in other their outward conuerſation and behauiour, that the ſame be accordingly vſed and prouided, or
<pb facs="tcp:191720:7"/> elſe that the Church wardens doe preſent whether the fault bee in the Miniſter who will not weare the ſame, or in the Pariſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners who will not prouide thoſe ornaments neceſſary and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="articles">
            <head>Articles to be enquired of within the Archdeaconrie of Leicester.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>INprimis;</hi> whether the Church of your Pariſh,<note place="margin">Double bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices.</note> bee now va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant and deſtitute of an Incumbent, how long it hath ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayned, whether any ſequeſtration be granted of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fruits, to whom, and by whom? If it haue an Incumbent, what his name is, of what bringing vp and degrée in Schooles? what the valure of the liuing is in the Kings Bookes: who is the Patron by right or aduouſon: whether hee hath any more benefices or Eccleſiaſticall promotions: how many, and where: If hee lie not on his Benefice, to whom hee letteth his tithes, for what yearely commoditie the ordinary charges deducted: Whether the Curate be orderly and lawfully admitted vpon due triall &amp; examination of his ſufficiency and honeſty vnder the ſeale of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Whether Common Prayer be diſtinctly and audibly read within the Pariſh Church,<note place="margin">Church-books.</note> the Sacraments reuerently and orderly adminiſtred, &amp; whether for better performance of them, you haue a booke of Common prayer, two Pſalters, the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Bible, the Homilies, the Paraphraſes of <hi>Eraſmus</hi> in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh, the Table of the ten Commandements, a comely Table ſtanding vpon a frame for the holy Communion decently coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and a conuenient Communion cup, with a couer agréeable, and a ſéemely and decent Pulpit.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Whether your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate,<note place="margin">Monethly Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</note> be a painefull zealous, and diligent Preacher: at the leaſt whether he doth procure quarterly or Monthly Sermons, according as by du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie he is bound, eſpecially vpon ſuch daies as the holy Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion ſhall be miniſtred, for the better inſtruction and prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion towards that occaſion? and whether he doth duly and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly Catechize euery Sunday with expoſition of the ſame, for the better inſtruction of the youth of the Pariſh, and Chriſtian
<pb facs="tcp:191720:8"/> information of other the hearers, and whether ſuch as are to be Chatechized, attend orderly at the time to be inſtructed, or who they be that make default, or ſhew themſelues obſtinate there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. And whether your Miniſter doe carefully repaire to viſite the ſicke of your Pariſh, for their ſpirituall comfort, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly attend his charge in thoſe extremities. And further whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hee doth conferre with his Pariſhoners, eſpecially ſuch as he knoweth not throughly grounded in the way and knowledge of their ſaluation, for their better inſtruction, before they repaire to the holy Communion. And if any refuſe this neceſſarie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference offered by the Miniſter, not onely to ſtay them from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing, but alſo preſent what be their names, with their cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes pretended?</p>
            <p n="4">4 Whether your Miniſter doth admit any to the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion or to bee married, or to anſwere for Infants in Baptiſme, being not ſufficiently Catechized and able to yéeld an account of their Chriſtian faith,<note place="margin">Infants to contracts.</note> that whom conſcience will not allure al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt once to thinke ſeriouſly of the meanes of their ſaluation, yet other extraordinarie occaſions may driue for ſhame to ſome knowledge of Chriſtianitie?</p>
            <p n="5">5 Whether your Miniſter or any other of your Pariſh bée knowne or ſuſpected as fauourers of the Romiſh Church,<note place="margin">Ieſuites.</note> ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioritie, or Religion. And whether any runnagate Ieſuites or counterfeit Maſſing Prieſts, going out according to the order of their profeſſions, are knowne or ſuſpected to frequent or hau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to any perſon or perſons within your Pariſh, or ſometime for a ſhift to lie or lurke with them: and whether they or any Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter, or any other pretending the name of a ſeruant, are ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to allure and perſwade any within your Pariſh from the true ſinceritie of the Goſpell, now by publike authoritie eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, to the vſing of Mattins, Beads, and ſuch other vaine Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh triſhtraſh: or of any vnlawfull Popiſh books: And whether any be reputed or ſuſpected to bee reaccounted to the Church of Rome within your Pariſh, and what be their names? And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you know or haue heard of any ſometime in orders, that now doe liue as lay men?</p>
            <p n="6">6 Whether any of your Pariſh doe altogether abſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from Diuine Seruice, or doe ſeldome or negligently come to the Church, or doe not continue there without diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance of the Miniſter and congregation, not departing thence
<pb facs="tcp:191720:8"/> but vpon ſome iuſt and lawfull cauſe: And whether any of your Pariſhoners do not receiue the Communion, at the leaſt thrice in the yeare according to his Maieſties Lawes eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and whether any hauing diuers houſes of remoue, do ſhift from place to place, in colour to defeat the performance of their Chriſtian duties in thoſe behalfes, what they be, and the names of euery of the family that doth the like. And whether the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular twelue pence be leuied according to the ſtatute?</p>
            <p n="7">7 Whether any within your Pariſh haue any of their kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red or kinſfolke beyond the Seas, what be their names, and how long they haue continued out of the Realme, and what by hereſay, or in conſcience you iudge their affection to be in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: or whether any are knowne or ſuſpected to relieue any ſuch.</p>
            <p n="8">8 Whether your Miniſter kéepe any ſuſpected woman in his houſe, or be giuen to drunkenneſſe, idleneſſe, or be a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Tauernes, Ale-houſes, or other ſuſpected places, or be Hunters, Hawkers, Dicers, Carders, Tablers, Swearers, or any waies giue any euill example of life or vnſéemely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parrell, to the offence of others, and diſcredit of their calling. And whether they be reported or ſuſpected to haue come by their benefice, or other Eccleſiaſticall promotions, Simonical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, directly or indirectly.</p>
            <p n="9">9 Whether there belong any glebe Lands to your Parſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, or Vicarage, and how many ſeuerall parcels there bee, and how much they containe by eſtimation, whether any be alienated, exchanged or incroched vpon, to the decay of the liuing? And whether your Chancell, and Parſonage houſes, be in good and ſufficient reparations, and whether your Church be in euery part ſo maintained as were conuenient. And whether your Church yards be throughly fenced about, and cleanly kept, and who is the cauſe of any of theſe defaults. And whether any Patrons haue decayed the Parſonage-hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and kept a ſtipendarie Prieſt in place, where an Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent ſhould be poſſeſſed?</p>
            <p n="10">10 Whether your Miniſter kéepe well your Regiſters of all Weddings, Burials, and Chriſtnings within your Pariſh ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Maieſties lawes eſtabliſhed, and doe preſent a copie of them once euery yeare by Indenture to the Chancellor or his Deputie, to remaine of record in the principall Office.</p>
            <p n="11">
               <pb facs="tcp:191720:9"/>11 Whether any within your Pariſh adminiſter the goods of thoſe that be dead, without lawfull authoritie: or any are ſuſpected to haue ſuppreſſed or altered the laſt wil of the dead, or any Executors that haue not fulfilled the teſtators wil, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in performing of the Legacies giuen to other good vſes or maintenance of the poore.</p>
            <p n="12">12 Whether you haue a Schoolemaſter within your Pariſh, and whether your Schoolemaſter teaching publikely or priuate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, be of good and ſincere Religion and conuerſation, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be examined and allowed by the Ordinary or his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer, according to the late Canons in that behalfe. And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any liuing giuen towards the erection or maintenance of any Schoole, bee with holden backe, or otherwiſe any wayes imployed.</p>
            <p n="13">13 Whether any haue pulled downe or diſcouered any Church, Chauncell, or Chappell, Porch, Veſtry, Stéeple, Bells, or any part of them, or felled Wood or Timber in the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard. And whether your Hoſpitals, or Spittels, be well and godly vſed and maintained according to the foundation and ancient Ordinances of the ſame?</p>
            <p n="14">14 Whether any entertainment be giuen, or gaming vſed in any Innes or Alehouſes, or other Victualers in time of Diuine Seruice or Sermons. Or whether any Butchers, Victua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, Pedlers, or other Artificers in time of common Prayer or Sermon, open their ſhops or wares: and whether your Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter cuſtomably remembreth your Church-Wardens and Swornemen, to attend their charge in ſuch behalfe?</p>
            <p n="15">15 Whether your Church goods, Stocks, or Rents, be let to the beſt commoditie, and for ſuch vſes as they were firſt meant, or now are to be imployed, and conuerted, &amp; no other waies. Or whether the ſame be increaſed or decayed, by what meanes, who being Church-Wardens, whether any are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde with making their accounts, or be thought not to haue made the true perfect and ſufficient account, what Lands or Stockes ſhould be, or yet remaine?</p>
            <p n="16">16 Whether any within your Pariſh, be ſuſpected to vſe ſorcerie, wichcraft, charmes, vnlawfull prayers, or innouati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in Latine or Engliſh: namely, Midwiues in the time of Womens trauaile with child, and who reſort to ſuch for helpe or Counſell?</p>
            <p n="17">
               <pb facs="tcp:191720:9"/>17 Whether the Miniſter or Church-wardens haue ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red any Lords of miſ-rule, or Summer Lords, or Ladies or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſguiſed perſons, as Morris dancers, to come vnreuerently piping, dancing or playing in the Church or Church-yard, with vnſéemely ſcoffes, ieſts, or ribauldrie, in time of Diuine ſeruice or Sermons, and what they bée that commit ſuch diſorders, and the company that maintained them?</p>
            <p n="18">18 Whether any of your Pariſh haue beene married within the degrées of affinitie, and conſanguinitie, forbidden by the Lawes of God: and whether for the better knowledge and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of thoſe degrées, you haue the table of degrées publikely affixed in your Pariſh Church: and whether any diuorced or ſeparated for marrying within thoſe degrées be notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding conuerſant, and kéepe companie together: whether any man bee ſuſpected to haue two wiues, or any woman two huſbands, or any married without banes thrice ſolemnly aſked, or out of the Pariſh, where one of them at leaſt doe inhabit: and whether any married, liue a part, and not continue together, according to the Lawes of God, and this Realme.</p>
            <p n="19">19 Whether any of your Pariſh be knowne, defamed or ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently ſuſpected of any notorious ſinne, fault or crime, as of vſury, ſwearing adultery, fornication, inceſt, baudery, drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, ribauldry, ſlander, contention, ſowing of diſcord betwéene neighbours, priuie receiuing women vnlawfully begotten with child, or ſuffering them to depart before publike ſatiſfaction made to the congregation. Or whether there bee any fighters, quarrellers, brawlers, or chiders in Church or Churchyard, any ſcoffers, rimers, or derides of Miniſters, or any that lay violent hande on them or any of them, or otherwiſe abuſe them.</p>
            <p n="20">20 All and euery the particulars of the premiſſes you are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently to enquire of and as well the Miniſters ſeuerally as the Church-wardens and Sidemen ioyntly to preſent the defaults of euery of them in writing ſubſcribed by their names: and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally whatſoeuer breaches and offences elſe they ſhall know or heare committed, againſt any of the Kings Maieſties Iniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, or any Eccleſiaſticall Lawes of this Realme?</p>
         </div>
         <div type="oath">
            <pb facs="tcp:191720:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Oath of the Church-wardens.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OV ſhall faithfully adminiſter all ſuch Church-goods as are or ſhal come to your hands to the vſe of your Church, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of make a true and faithfull account at the end of your Office, deliuering all that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth therupon to your next ſucceſſors. Alſo you ſhall diligently enquire of, and faithfully preſent all ſuch perſons, as you ſhall either vpon your owne know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, or by publike fame vnderſtand to be guiltie of any of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence or fault mentioned in any of theſe Articles aforeſaid, or any other fault which is to be puniſhed by the lawes Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall of this Realme, wherein you ſhall not preſent any perſon for malice, hatred or euill will, nor ſpare any for fauour, feare, or any corrupt affection, but you ſhall faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully diſcharge your conſciences, as men hauing the feare of God before your eyes, and ſeeking the reformation of his Church, So God helpe you in Chriſt our Sauiour.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:191720:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
